A Finding Aid to the Dorothy Block Papers, 1925-1985, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Dorothy Block papers
1925-1985
Archives of American Art
Block, Dorothy, 1904-1984
AAA.blocdoro
Archival Resource Key
0.7 Linear feet
The scattered papers of painter Dorothy Block measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1925 to 1982. Found are biographical materials, correspondence, photographs of Block and of works of art, printed material, a mixed media scrapbook, sketches, and writings. Also found are clippings and a photo of the artwork of Louis Keila, Block's uncle.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The scattered papers of painter Dorothy Block measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1925 to 1982. Found are biographical materials, correspondence with Dorothy Grotz, Aristodemos Kaldis, Jacob Lawrence, and others, photographs of Block and of works of art, printed material, a mixed media scrapbook, sketches, and writings. Also found are clippings and a photo of the artwork of Louis Keila, Block's uncle.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 3481 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm
Biographical / Historical
Dorothy Block (1904-1984) was a painter active in New York City, New York. Block studied and later taught at the Art Students League and participated in the Federal Art Project.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Dorothy Block and her sister Lillian MacKendrick donated Block's papers to the Archives of American Art in 1975 and 1977. Additional material was donated in 1990 by Robert Dublirer, widower of Dorothy Block.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Women painters; Scrapbooks; Kaldis, Aristodimos, 1899-1979; Grotz, Dorothy; Lawrence, Jacob, 1917-2000; Federal Art Project; Art Students League (New York, N.Y.)
- Dorothy Block Papers, 1925-1985; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2, BV 3
  Scope and Contents
  Artwork consists of eleven sketches by Block. Biographical data includes a copy of Block's transcript from the Art Students League, an award, and her obituary. Correspondence is with Dorothy Grotz, Aristodemos Kaldis, Jacob Lawrence, and others. A file on Block's uncle Louis Keila consists of a photo of Keila's sculpture and two clippings.
  Photographs depict Block, her family, Michael Freilich, Aristodemos Kaldis, and William von Schlegell; works of art; and an exhibition. Printed material includes clippings and exhibition announcements and catalogs. Writings by Block reflect on her career and the art world, including an article titled "Some Thoughts on Where We Stand" (1972), a fragment of her memoir, and reminiscences of the Federal Art Project.
  A mixed media scrapbook contains reproductions of famous paintings annotated by Block for children.
  - Artwork, Sketches, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)
  - Biographical Material, 1955-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - on Louis Keila, 1927-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Block, Family and Friends, 1927-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Exhibitions and Works of Art, circa 1950s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material, Clippings, 1965-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1925-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Volume 3)
  - Writings, circa 1960-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)